♪ Ain't no sunshine when she's gone ♪
♪ It's not warm when she's away ♪
♪ She's always gone too long ♪
♪Anytime she goes away ♪
♪ Wonder this time where she's gone ♪
♪ Wonder if she's going to stay ♪
♪ Ain't no sunshine when she's gone ♪
♪ And this house just ain't no home ♪
♪ Anytime she goes away ♪
♪ And I know, I know, I know, I know, ♪
♪ I know, I know, I know, I know, I know, ♪
♪ I know, I know, ♪
♪ Hey, I oughtta leave young thing alone ♪
♪ But ain't no sunshine when she's gone ♪
♪ Anytime she goes away ♪
♪Anytime she goes away ♪
[Crowd applause]
[Chattering on TV]
- Can I take this right back to when youas you first started.
How did your recording career come about?
- I saved up some of my own moneyand recorded it myself.
I had never written any songs.
I didn't really know how to play anythingand I had never sung before
not really--in the shower or some place
but I just decided it would be awfully niceto get into music business.
And I just walked around and knockedon everybody's door.
A lot of times I would go in and somebody would say to me--
You're too old to be just beginning.You know, I was like 32 years old at the time.
Most of the major record companiescall me up,
but they had a different idea of how--they don't want me to do anything quiet.
They had this rhythm and blues syndromein their mind with the horns
and the three chicksand the gold lame suit, you know.
And I wasn't really into that,I had a job, so I thought,
If they won't let me do itlike I want to do it,
"I got this good job, making these
toilets, I don't need you cats."
- [laughing] "Making these toilets"?
What kind of toilet were you making?
- Yeah. For aircraft.- Ah!
- Yeah, 747 aircraft.
I installed cameras in those toilets.
Unbeknownst, we say that in _____
to anybody but me.- [laughing]
- So if you've ever been to the bathroom
on a 747, I know you very well!
[Laughter and applause]
- So...
here's all the stuff that I don't knowhow to work. [laughing]
- I mean, I guess the stuff works,
I know how to turn it on, you know--
Like I can make lights come on and stuff.Let's see...
Yeah, I can turn that on and--
And, let's see...
Turn this fan on here to cool that down.This thing has been sitting here
corroding for about 10 years.
[unintelligible] I think I got a speaker
thing here...
Fooling around, let's see.
I was just playing with all these gadgets.
[drum beats]
♪ [music] ♪
I have to be careful that I don't just
wallow in my own comfort.
Probably now, I'm trying to findsome kind of motivation or, you know--
I'm not lazy.
I don't even understand.
I'm trying to give myself a chanceto get driven.
Where just the sheer activityof doing something just jacks you up,
makes you excited.
♪ [music] ♪
I lived a good portion of my lifebefore I started to play music.
I had been working at Weber Aircraftand I got laid off.
Then Ain't No Sunshine startedappearing on the radio and stuff.
And it's funny, because I gottwo requests in the same day.
I got a letter from my jobsaying that I was called back to work
And I got request to dothe Johnny Carson Show.
♪ [music] ♪[applause]
- I like that song,that was big for you, wasn't it?
- Yeah! That kind of got me off the hamand eggs thing
and kind of tightened me up a little bit.
- We mentioned this before,that you were a craftsman
and you made toilets, right?
- Oh, yeah! It was a good job.I had a lot of fun doing it.
[Laughter]
- Where does the fun come in, Bill?[Laughter]
- The people in my own family were probablysurprised when I was on the radio.
People that I had been in the Navy with,people I had worked in a factory with,
people that knew me were probably going,Wait a minute, is that that same guy?
♪ [music] ♪
- If I would have goneto work the next day,
and told somebody where I was last night,I would have got laughed out of the place.
All of a sudden,I'm travelling on the road
and more people are interestedin you than before.
It was just like a whole other world.
♪ You just call on me brother ♪♪ When you need a hand ♪
♪ We all need somebody to lean on... ♪
- Ladies and gentlemen, Mr. Bill Withers!
[applause]
♪ ..that you'll understand ♪♪ We all need somebody to lean on ♪
♪ Lean on me... ♪- Mr Bill Withers.
[applause]
♪ ..when you're not strong ♪♪ And I'll be your friend ♪
♪ I'll help you carry on ♪
♪ For it won't be long ♪♪ Till I'm gonna need ♪
♪ Somebody to lean on... ♪
[guitar playing]♪ [music] ♪
- New words started to enter my lifethat had never been there before,
like handsome.
Boy, you sure do get better-lookingwhen you get a hit record, I'll tell you that.
♪ I want to spread the news ♪♪ That if it feels this good getting used ♪
♪ Oh you just keep on using me ♪
♪ Hey, hey, until you use me up ♪
♪ Hey, hey ♪
♪ Talking about you using mebut it all depends on what you do ♪
♪ It ain't too bad the wayyou're using me♪
♪ Coz I sure am using you to dothat thing you do ♪
♪ Hey, hey, to do that thing you do...♪
- I had never been in theentertainment business before.
The first live singing I did wasin front of about 5,000 people.
All of a sudden, somebody says,"Go to work."
- Let's give a big round of applause for the one and only Mr. Bill Withers!
[cheering and applause]
♪ Well, I'm five years old ♪♪ Sure am cold ♪
♪ Mama's out cooking steak ♪♪ Cooking steak for someone else... ♪
- What you see is the prognosisof your career, Bill?
You know, you'll become a big star,you're becoming a superstar.
And do think you can remainjust as you are, still Bill?
- First, I have to become somebodythat understands what prognosis means!
- Well, how do you interprethow things are going to go for you?
- Oh, yeah! I'm kinda justletting them go, you know.
Letting them go, and whatever is givento me, if I can do it, I'll just have at it.
Two or three years into this,I was in a major mess.
I mean I got a record companyactually collapsed out from under me.
Well, IRS came in and took the tapesand sold them.
Then when I went to this major,big, mega label,
you know, you walk in, you play something,somebody goes,
"Where are the horns?"
"You got to put some horns on it.How long is the intro?"
First hit record I had wasAin't No Sunshine.
No intro, nothing.
If nobody throws all the rules at you,you might make a song with no introduction.
Instead of singing aboutromantic love all the time,
you make a love songabout your grandmother.
Or you make a friendship song,a-la Lean On Me.
Searching through your feelingsand your vulnerabilities
and your strengths and your weaknesses.
You're already loaded up enough
with the burden of just trying to find those feelings
So then, here comes a whole bunch of guys,
trying to tell you what to do with alltheir goofy sad suggestions and stuff
They had the R&B black guys, and thenthey got what I like to call Blacksperts,
that's the white guyswho are supposed to be experts.
You know, who have some kind of tapinto your black psyche.
I had an A&R man once.
His big suggestion to me was thatI cover Elvis Presley's In The Ghetto.
I was livid, and as I startedto try to respond to that,
that simple kind of emotional,vulnerable kind of thing,
kind of got splattered around.
[Applause]
I became very interested.
Can I still stay in this businessand be effective and make a living
and not have to play this fame game?
I wasn't any good at it.The fame game was kicking my ass.
♪ I see the crystal raindrops fall ♪♪ And the beauty of it all ♪
♪ Is when the sun comes shining through ♪ ♪ To make those rainbows in my mind ♪
♪ When I think of you some time ♪ ♪ And I want to spend some time with you ♪
♪ Just the two of us ♪
♪ We can make it if we try ♪ ♪ Just the two of us ♪
♪ Building castles in the sky ♪ ♪ Just the two of us You and I... ♪
♪ [music] ♪
- I would like to see us move past
to where you need the validation of themainstream so much...
until we got away from liking ourselves.
- The challenge, though, is still,once you get in that mainstream
to not become mainstream. That is to say,to remain your authentic self,
to still make the communitythat produced you, proud of you.
To not, in the cultural vernacular,to become a sell-out.
- Sell-out? I'm not crazy aboutthat word...
because...we're all entrepreneurs.
To me...
I don't care whether you owna furniture store or whatever,
the best sign you can put up is,
"Sold out".- Sold out.
- So let's--- [men laughing]
- Can we make that...[men laughing]
- Can we make that subservient?[speech overlap]
- It is a profound point.
One, is a Shakespearian point.
To thine own self be true.- [Bill] Uh-huh
- If night follows the day,thou can be false to no one.
You have been true to yourself.
You don't sound like Paul Simonon the guitar.
You're Bill Withersbecause you come out of your roots.
When you sing Grandma's Hands,you start talking about Matty,
and talking about grandmataking care of local, unwed mothers
in Virginia, West Virginia, that's real.That's being yourself.
At the same time, in being yourself,you're able to cross over
into a white mainstream, and they hadto accept you on your own terms.
- You see, looking at this thing is... - You gotta be careful.
- ...not new.
Oh, boy, these pages are really--
Well, I guess this was brothersand sisters I had that never lived.
I was the last of 13 kidsthat my mother had.
I guess I wasn't born yet,so I'm not in here anywhere.
Grackus Monroe Gallowaywas my mother's father.
He was born a slave.
He was probably nine years oldwhen they freed the slaves.
He worked in the coal mines but he wouldnever work for the coal company.
He hauled coal--here's Grandma.
Now, I took this picture when I was a kid,
so you can see what year it was by the car.
Most of us at some point in our liveshave somebody that means more to us
than anyone else that has ever meantbefore or will ever mean again.
Sometimes it's a long-legged lady,if you're a man,
or some tall, very smoothed man,if you're a woman.
But in my case, I learned how to reallylove somebody from just a nice old lady.
My favorite thing that I've written has to beabout this favorite old lady of mine.
♪ [music] ♪
♪ Mm-mm, mm-mm ♪♪ Mm-mm, mm-mm ♪
- I'm from Slab Fork, West Virginia.You know where that is, right?
- No. Is that any place near Bluefield?- Yeah, you know where it is.
- Yeah, it's near Bluefield. About 30or 40 miles, I guess, from Bluefield.
- Slab Fork, West Virginia?- Yeah.
♪ Mm-mm, mm-mm ♪♪ Mm-mm ♪
♪ Grandma's hands clappedin church on Sunday morning ♪
♪ Grandma's hands playeda tambourine so well ♪
♪ Grandma's hands usedto issue out a warning ♪
♪ She's say, "Billy, don't you run so fast"♪♪ "Might fall on a piece of glass" ♪
♪ "Might be snakes there in that grass" ♪♪ Grandma's hands ♪
♪ Ah, them Grandma's hands ♪♪ Mm-mm, mm-mm... ♪
- Hey, CV.- [man talking]
- This is the mayor here,this is Mayor CV.
- [CV] How you doing?- CV's running the things.
- How you doing?- I'm good, man.
CV was talking to my daughterand he was telling her, you know,
"Let me tell you about yourgreat-grandmother."
- Right.- And so CV remembers her.
- Grandmother Galloway. She was a very elegant woman.
She sat on this porch and she wouldsing spirituals right on that porch
and clap her hands.
[CV clapping]
- Remember they called it getting happy.- Right, right, right!
- There's a saying, The sleepy smilingSouth with blood on its mouth.
- Right, right.- Well, we weren't in that South.
This was South, in a way.
Like, when we grew up, you didn'thave to sit on the back of the bus.
- Right, right. - But we had separate schools.
- Right.
- You had to go to the back doorif you wanted a milkshake or something
from one of the restaurants uptown.- Right.
- But the kids left their own devices,we played, now--
We sat here--that was the dividing line.- Right.
- We were the only two black familieson this side of the railroad track.
- [CV] On this side of the raidroad.
- [Bill] Well, we just integratedthe whole thing by ourselves.
- [CV] I think all of the black familiesbasically, like it or not,
most of us had white peoplein our families.
- [Bill] You know, after you dida day's work in the coal mines,
- everybody was black anyway. [laughing]- [CV] Yeah, yeah, yeah, well, that's true.
That's true. - Were nothing but black people here.
- [Bill] I haven't been to Slab Forksince about 1959.
- Nobody's back there. There's nothingthere much except graves, you know--
and old coal mines.
I'm really not too hung up on goingand laying flowers on dead people.
Let me be very candid about it.This was a white graveyard.
This is a black graveyard.
- Hey, Bill Withers. - Yeah?
- What was your brother's name?
- His name was Earl Martin.
- Here he is right here.
- Okay.
- Earl W. Martin.
- Yeah, that's my brother.
- Well, they give him a nice stone.Where do you see those number--oh, 1942.
- Do you vaguely remember any locationabout where your father would be?
- No.
And I don't know whether he wouldbe buried close to Earl or not.
- Yeah, well, Papa, where ever your at, hello, bud. I'll catch you something later.
♪ [music] ♪
- My father taught me, you know--He put the work thing in my head
- My mother put the moral thingin my head.
My father used to havea little barbershop here
and he wasn't a good barberbut he told great stories.
♪ Just can't keep from crying ♪♪ Six years, Lucy ♪
♪ Lord, have mercy that's a long time ♪♪ That's a long time.♪
- All these houses were owned by thecoal company
and they all looked the same.
- [CV] Absolutely.
- They've probably done stuff to them now.
- [CV]The company owned everything.
- [Billy] Which was one family.
The coal company got your money,they paid you, then you had to shop--
you shopped in their store. Now, this was the old store.
- [CV]Yeah, company store. - You could buy everything at this store.
- [CV] Now, this is an exceptionalcoal camp from the standpoint that
it still have enough life to havesome people living here.
- They had a lot of churches.They had a Baptist church,
then they had a Methodist church somewhere.- [CV] Uh-huh.
- And then they had your Holy andSanctified Church.
♪ Remember me... ♪
- I liked my grandmother's church.It was spontaneous singing.
There was no programmed singing.
Somebody got up and startedto sing a song, everybody sung.
It was my favorite kind of singing.
♪ Remember me ♪♪ Oh, Lord ♪
♪ Remember me.♪
- [Bill] Well, we have walked theserailroad ties, huh, CV?
- [CV] Yeah.
Now, if you want to testhow skillful you are, walk this.
- Remember that used to be the thing,who could walk the rail?
- [CV] If you can walk the rail--- --[Bill] the furthest.
- See, that's how to test how skillful you are. - [Bill] Look at you.
- Yeah, see. I still can walk it.
- You doing tricks and stuff.
- Yeah. See, that's how skillful.
- Now if you break out a handstand,I'm leaving tonight.
[CV laughing]
- I'm telling you, this was like,life, busy, busy,
Summertime come, we'd go around,dam up the creek, get buck naked.
- And go swimming.
- Go swimming, and so the girlswould time you out, say,
"Well, it's about swimming time,"then the girls would come down there.
- Yeah.- And stand on the side
so you couldn't get out of the wateruntil they left.
- Right! [laughing]
- So it's just a whole culturalof stuff like that.
- [CV] It's an amazing thing,when you look back,
and you realize that the world changedcompletely around you.
- It's gone, brother. This has gone.- You're seeing what used to be.
- [Bill] So we are truly the last of a--- [CV] Yeah, we getting there.
- [Bill] of a breed, huh.- [CV] Yeah, we getting there.
- Hey, Bill.- Yeah?
- Sing it one time for me.♪ Ain't no sunshine when she's gone. ♪
- You already hit it.I can't hit it like you no more.
- Let me ask you, do you do any--Do you go on any tours at all now?
- The first thing you said to me was,"You look like an old man."
- Right! [laughing]- So, now, how could you tell me in one breath
that I look like an old manand then in the second breath tell me,
"You ought to be out on the road,playing rock and roll"?
- No. I have never understood how you,entertainers, could be on the road
and do every-other-nightor one-night stands.
- I don't understand it either,that's how come I ain't doing it.
[both laughing]
- I've had people ask me thatquestion a lot.
You know, "How could you just stop?"
Well, to me, it wasn't stopping anything. It was doing something else.
I mean, I like music, but I'm notgoing to place my whole worth on it.
You know how unhappy you would beif you thought that
the way you are is not okay?
I started out my life like that.I don't want to end it up like that.
♪ [music] ♪
- [Marcia Withers]Okay, we're onour way to get a birthday cake.
I'm getting just a "7-0". I don't want himto have to struggle to blow out 70 candles.
We are putting this here.- [Bill talking]
- This doesn't seem very formal, but, you know--- [Bill] Doug.
- Yes?- You cool?
- Uh-huh.[Bill talking]
- But we still have to celebrate.
We would love you to make a giganticwish and blow out your candles.
You don't have to divulge the wishbut we'd love you to make a wish.
[Bill blows the candle][applause]
- I'm a senior citizen.
- That's okay with me.
- I'm OK with my grey hairand my narrowing shoulders.
To the Country Inn.
The most important thing isto be okay, you know.
I just want to feel good.
I know what it feels likenot to feel all right.
You know, guilt and regret,aches and pains.
I'd really like to learn to accepteverything before I die.
- [Jimmy] Hey, Bill. - [Bill] Hey, man, how you doing?
Look out! Ah, Jimmy my boy.- [Jimmy] What's going on, bud?
- How you doing, boy?You still look like a teenager.
[laughing together]- How you doing?
- [Jimmy] Good seeing you, Bill.- [Bill] You too, man, you too.
- [Jimmy] He must be your son.- Yep.
- [laughing] Looks just like you!
- [Bill] How are you doing, man?How's everything? How's everything going?
- I'm his daughter, but last timeI remember you, you held me on your lap.
We went over to your mom's house.- Yeah. How you doing, sugar?
Well, you could still sit on there.You know, not too long, though.
[woman laughing]- Not too long, though.
♪ [music] ♪♪ When I wake up in the morning, love. ♪
[people chattering]
♪ And something without warning, love♪
♪ Then I look at you ♪♪ And the world's all right with me. ♪
- [Bill] You're looking good, man.- Thank you. You're looking great!
- I actually turned 70 today.
- Oh, wow.
- Some people are just born cool.They'd been cool all their lives.
Well, I hadn't been cool all my life.
I was an asthmatic stutterer as a kid.
One popular thing is,"Spit it out! Spit it out!"
And then they have all thesefolky kind of cures,
like hitting you in the face with a dishragor something, you know what I mean.
Really stupid stuff, you know.
I grew up with, "You can't do nothing."
One teacher said to me oncethat I was handicapped.
And I didn't like that word.
So any dreams that I had,I kept them to myself.
Once you're labeled sortof a less-than person,
it gave me this crisis of confidence.
I just wanted to leave. And then goand start over with some new people.
♪ [music] ♪
The Navy, at that age, you know, 17,seemed like somewhere to go.
♪ If you don't look into your mind ♪♪ And find out what you're running from ♪
♪ Tomorrow might be justanother day to run. ♪
These are my old Navy buddies.I've known these guys since I was 21.
We all met in Guam.
There was not much for usto do socially.
So it was frustrating becauseyou got all these young guys,
with all this testosterone.And there's nowhere for them to go.
- Good old Bill.[Bill laughing]
- This is the man.[laughing together]
- [Mervin Johnson] You know whatthey told me about Guam?
The guy says, "Oh, you're going to Guam."There's a woman behind every tree."
There's only two trees.[laughing together]
- [Bill] It was hard on a brother in Guam.It's funny times.
- That was a whole lot of life real fast.- Yeah.
- [Mervin] On the way over,I was thinking that--
When I first seen you, didn't you bringa guitar to Guam?
- [Bill] No. No. I never owned a guitaruntil 1970 or something like that.
- [Mervin] Is that right?
- Yeah, I don't know an F-Sharpfrom Ninth Street.
- [Mervin] And when you got thereyou found that little old bar.
You were singing Johnny Mathis, more so--
- [Bill] Or whatever the piano player could play.
- Is that right?
- Couple of drinks, man,everybody, you know--you start singing.
- Shoot. Yeah.
- [Bill] But I still hadn't given it anythought as to making a living out of it.
♪ When you appeared in my imagination. ♪
- [Terrell Harrison] He's always beenjust Bill Withers to me.
And I'm sure that's what you feel too.
And I don't think he would want itany different.
- [Bill] My real life was whenI was just a working guy.
Just in the Navy, just a mechanic,you know what I mean.
But the true measure ofany group of people is,
"How are the ones that are just people?"
♪ You were here in my memory ♪♪ And I love you now that you're here. ♪
- I was an aircraft mechanic.I was in the Navy nine years.
- Okay.- Is that right?
- How do you do that? - I can do masonry and all these things.
- Now--
- Were you writing songs while doing that?
- I've written songs workingat McDonnell Douglas.
Use me, you know, working on anairplane and things. [laughing]
- Grandma's Hands, Weber Aircraftin Burbank. [laughing]
- Is that right?- You understand what I'm saying?
- You work and write--- ...working on the thing.
and singing it over and over to yourself
so you don't forget it before you get home.
- Oh, wow![laughing]
- You know what's funny? People say,"He wrote that song about that woman."
I didn't know none of them damn women when I was writing them songs.
- Just in your mind?- I couldn't get no women,
I was making three dollars an hourworking in the damn thing.
- Uno, dos, tres, cuatro.
♪ [music] ♪
- I was 23 years old,
I was a graduate student, UCLA,working on my MBA.
And my sister and I decided we wanted--well, actually, it was me.
I wanted to go see Gil Scott-Heron.
♪ [music] ♪
There's a vacant table.
She said, "Oh, let's go sit there."I said, "It says reserved."
And lo and behold,it was Bill sitting there,
which I didn't know, she recognized him.And that's how I met him.
- I wasn't starstruck at all.He was this regular, normal person.
He was interesting.He was interested in me.
♪ When I'm kissing my love ♪♪ Thump-a-thumping in my head ♪
♪ Now, when I'm kissing my love ♪♪ I close my eyes and see ♪
♪ A pretty city with a million flowers in it. ♪
- A lot of men can't expresswhat they're feeling, and he can.
He's sensitive but tough.
♪ Put your foot on the rockand put your foot, don't stop ♪
♪ Put your foot on the rock ♪
♪ Put your foot on the rockI know you just can't stop ♪
♪ When I'm kissing my love ♪♪ Feel the blood pumping in my veins ♪
♪ Now, when I'm kissing my love ♪ ♪ She's such a tender sender ♪
♪ With her sweet young frame ♪♪ Ah, ha, ha ♪
♪ She's so good at what she does ♪♪ All she wants to do is kiss and hug ♪
♪ She's got me in love and I can feel my heart ♪
♪ Just pumping and skipping ♪
♪ When I'm kissing my love. ♪
- *As soon as I figured out who I was,
I married an MBA. You know what I mean?
The one thing about Marcia, Marcia is anoptimist in the face of everything.
- We live a life that iscomfortable and simple,
and I think that Bill never really wantedall these riches and material things.
When the kids came along,he was home a lot.
He didn't do a lot of touring.
There were times when I'm surehe really missed being in the business,
making music, but I think that it was more important for him
to have a life and a family.
He had never had a family before.
He had his mother, but his dad diedwhen he was 13,
and it was really important for himto be a father to the kids.
♪ [music] ♪
♪ I get a warm summer feeling ♪♪ Walking through the snow ♪
♪ Even chilly darkness ♪♪ Has the brightest glow ♪
♪ And I just love you so. ♪
- [Todd Withers] From very early on,my father played a lot of music at home.
Music was never something that waspushed, it was just always there.
We had two pianos at home,on opposite sides of the house.
It certainly was somethingthat blended the family together,
it was something we all shared.
- [Bill talking]...you get it?- [Marcia] Okay. You're the navigator.
- [Todd] Okay.
- [Bill] You're getting the tour--
- [Bill] This was Todd's big day.He's accepted into this law school.
- [Marcia] Exciting!
- It's exciting for him and it's exciting for us.
I really learned about this wholefamily thing from Marcia.
I think the older you get, the more yourconcerns shifts from you to other people.
- So, Todd, do I have to start calling youmister in a couple years?
- [Kori Withers] Growing up listeningto my dad's songs was just
the most peaceful space I rememberbeing able to have as a child.
And he kind of speaks in little poems.
You know, the sky is blueand I'm happy to see you.
You know, he'd just pull it out of anywhere.
Quit crying and start trying.
A lot of times he says,"Write this down."
He says, "Get a pencil, write this down"
And I'm sure my mother has hundreds oflittle pieces of paper all over the house,
--just not even full songs, but two lines.You know, just a thought.
Sometimes he'll call me just to say that,
"I was thinking thisand want you to make a note of it."
And then some of these things,I think, make it into Songville.
Growing up, I always wanted to bejust like my dad, really.
When I started writing songs,it just took a lot of courage to say
that's really, secretly, what I want to do.
♪ Paint a portrait of tomorrow ♪♪ With no colors from today. ♪
- I always wanted to write,but I always thought,
"How could I ever come close todoing the types of things that he did?"
Just because I know I'm a different person.
I knew I wasn't going to sit downthe first time I picked up a guitar
and write Ain't No Sunshine,but I know what he thinks is good.
I really didn't want to shareanything with him.
I ended up playing somethingfor him when I wasn't ready,
and he was just like,"No, this is not happening."
It was hard for me because I needed him
to just be my dad and say,
"I'm proud of you're working on something"
or "I'm excited about your journey."
And I mean, it was none of that.
- [Bill] One thing I always tell my kids is,"It's okay to head out for wonderful,"
"but on your way to wonderful,you have to pass through all right."
"And when you get to all right,take a good look around and get used to it,"
"because that may be as faras you're gonna go."
Most people don't knowor don't care who you are.
I think I'm kind of like pennies.
You have them in your pocketbut don't remember they're there.
Nobody knows who I am.
Sometimes if I tell somebody who I am,they'll say, "No, you ain't."
Or people just don't know,never did and don't care.
I don't work the circuit whereyou keep reminding people of you.
This is my first tribute kind-of-thing.
- [Nona Hendryx] We're here tonightfor Bill Withers
and his amazing catalogue of music.
An amazing vocalist, songwriter, musician,
and someone I've loved and appreciatedfor many many years.
So congratulations, Bill, and youcoming out to support him, thank you!
- Brooklyn's own, Corey Glover!
[Corey Glover singing]
♪ A man we passed just triedto stare me down ♪
♪ And when I looked at you,you looked at the ground ♪
♪ Now, I don't know who he is,but I think that you do. ♪
- Y'all know this one, don't you?
♪ Dag gummit, who is heand what is he to you? ♪
♪ Memories take you back to the good times when it's over and the sad times disappear.♪
- [Bill] It would be kind of rough,right now, to just go out there and just say,
"I wanted to see how many peopleI can make notice me."
There was a time when that was it.
I wanted everybody to look at me andeverybody to want to know me
and everybody was--There was a time for that.
This is not that time.
What if I had to get up from here right now,and about nine o'clock tonight,
start trying to kick up a ruckus? [Bill laughing]
I'm not feeling that way.
No matter how many people say,"You should feel that way."
I can't.
If I was completely honest with myself,I'm probably a little manic-depressive.
That's why maybe I might writesome songs that might reach
somebody else's emotions,because I have some.
I have my own.
Wouldn't it be fun to all of a sudden,just jump up and start shaking it around?
That'd be something, huh? If I just had some showing-off steroids,
man, you would get tired of me,you know what I mean?
I just wanna--I want to. I want to.I watch other people show off, and I say,
"Man, I used to want to show off."If I could just get moved to.
I need a little injectionin my showing-off gland.
♪ Memories are that way ♪
- [Ralph MacDonald] Is he going tosing again? What's he doing?
I would love to see Bill singanother record.
There's millions and millions of people thatwould love to see--hear Bill Withers again.
If he wants to do it, fine. If he don'twanna do it, I respect that too,
because what he's been through,with the record business and his life,
and to come through it,I may not want to sing again neither.
- [Jim James] In some ways I think it'sreally cool that he hasn't made
a record since 1985.
Because if he feels likehe hasn't anything to say,
or he just wanted to focus onhis family, and stuff like that,
you've got to define your prioritiesfor yourself.
- [Angelique Kidjo] For me, it showsthe artist that he is.
It's not only about money,it's about the beauty of the song.
For him not to write a songand any album for 23 years,
from me to him, I say, Respect Maestro.
- [James Gadson] It would be great to dosome stuff with Bill again.
It would be--you know,I've always thought about that.
We haven't played together for,I guess, 30 years.
In my career, that was probablythe best times that I had.
- [Benorce Blackmon] No tellingwhat might happen.
Bill might pop upand next thing you know,
we're in the studio doing something.
But he's always doing something,don't think Bill's not recording.
He's doing something, writing.It's in his blood.
Just like it's in mine bloodto play this guitar.
It's in his blood to write.Something might pop up.
I stay optimistic.
But until then, I'll keep on grooving.[laughing]
- The hardest thing to be in songwritingis to be simple and yet profound.
And it's difficult. It's a very difficult art form.
Some people have it intrinsically,some people have to work very hard,
but Bill seemed to understandintrinsically, instinctively, how to do that.
- [Clarence Avant] Bill Withers couldwork a lot and make a whole lot of money
if he wanted to do that. But I don't thinkhe's comfortable doing that.
Because I've call him--
People call me all the time,"Can I get Bill?"
I say, "Hey man, don't call me, becauseI don't think he's going to do it."
♪ [music] ♪
- [Bill] We are so remiss inover-valuing entertainers,
of which I am one, no problem.
And athletes and undervaluingthe people among us
who have less obvious gifts.
- Let me ask you this questionabout your own legacy,
both personally, as a human being,and as a great artist that you are,
what would you wantyour legacy to be?
- I'm in New York because I have the pleasure of being honored
by the Our Time Theatre Group,and that's for kids who stutter.
And it's a great thing,it's very close to my heart.
Having navigated through my youthand well into my adulthood
dealing with that issue,it's fun to see this thing grow.
[applause]♪ [music] ♪
I grew up in a place calledSlab Fork, West Virginia,
I'm sure you've been thereon many vacations. [crowd laughing]
Swam in our creek.
No disrespect to Slab Fork,it's a coal-mining camp.
And stuttering is rough for kids,but stuttering in Slab Fork, West Virginia,
let's just say, you don't go to Slab Forkon the scholarship.
[crowd laughing]
When you're a kid you want to be cool,and you want to be cool
with the cool people.
And that didn't always happen,
so if you can learn to valuethe people who value you.
And I was very moved when I saw thesekids talking about how much
they meant to each other.
I am honored to be honored,and let's hope that each kid
finds his own personal comfort zone,
where he can grow, and nurturewhatever gifts that he might have
because if you take away the peoplewho stutter from the world,
you're left with a whole bunch of chatty.
[crowd laughing]
Fill in your own word.
[crowd laughing and applauding]
- [Taro Alexander] The kids areso excited to meet you,
I've been playing your music,
and they cannot wait to meet youand talk with you.
- Yeah.- You are a role model for me and for them.
- Oh, thank you, bud.Yeah, let's go see them.
- Yeah, right here.
- Alright.- Come on in.
- Okay.
- Ladies and gentlemen,may I introduce Mr. Bill Withers!
[crowd applause]
- [Taro] Our time kids, feel freeto come up and introduce yourself.
[Kids shouting]- Yeah.
- Hi, my name is Victoria.- Hi, sweetie.
- Danielle.
- [Bill] Hi, sweetie.- [Danielle] Nice to meet you.
- Alright. How you feeling, bud? My man.- Good.
- What's your name?- Joe.
- All right, Joe.[Bill laughing]
You know what I noticedwhen we were meeting is,
it's almost like fingerprints. We eachhave our own style of stutterings,
which makes us unique. I really identifiedwith people who stop at their name.
Last night this friend of mine,who's a fairly well-known painter,
had this thing,so there were a lot of athletes
and people that I had seen in my life,
so I wanted to say hello to everybodyand introduce myself.
And I went over to this one guy,and man, I got stuck.
And it brought back memories becausethere was a woman with him
and she started to laugh.
It was fear. Fear of the perceptionof the listener.
This fear that makes us apprehensiveright at the point of trying to speak,
that stops us.
One of the ways to deal with the fearis to approach people
with a prepared forgiveness.
We have to be more civil thanmost people that we will encounter.
Having had people not understand mea lot, maybe helped me wait a little bit
to where I can extend something thathasn't been given to me.
And I think that makes youa much bigger person.
- [Taro] We are thrilled to have you here,
and everything that you said just meansso much to me personally,
and we'd love to sing for you today.
- [Bill] I would have been insulted if youwould have not done something for me.
[crowd laughing]
♪ Sometimes I feel like everyone'salways ignoring me ♪
♪ Sometimes I feel like everyone'salways ridiculing me ♪
♪ All I want in this whole worldis to be myself, and nobody else ♪
♪ All I want in this whole worldis love, is love, is love. ♪
[crowd singing together]♪ All I want in this world is love ♪
♪ All I want in this world is love ♪♪ All I want in this world is love. ♪
- Yeah![applause]
- I understood what you meant,you know.
There's an old Southern saying that says,
It don't sound right if it ain't said right.
So you guys are saying yourfeeling's right, so just keep doing that.
And it's really a big favor to me,for you guys to remind me
of some things that maybeI had forgotten.
And maybe to show me some thingsthat I didn't know.
So you guys are cool.[applause]
And next time I see youI probably won't be this nice.
[crowd laughing]
We have to make allowancesfor each other!
[Bill playing piano]
Thoreau, I think, said, The massof men lead lives of quiet desperation.
I would like to know how it feelsfor my desperation to get louder.
♪ [music] ♪
- [Bill] Yes, Raul Midon, please.
[Phone ringing]- Hello.
- Hello, Raul.- Yes.
- Hi, it is Bill Withers.How you doing, bud?
- Oh, good.
- I was hoping that at some pointor another, that you would maybe have
just a little time so we could justmess around, you know.
Just you and me, we could plunk around--
I'll even break outmy old Linn drum machine to--
[Raul laughing]- make some noise, you know what I mean?
- [Raul] I don't know what to say.
I'm just so happy that you're interested
and man, I'd love to put our heads together.
- I'd like to try something out on you, Raul.- Okay.
- Because I've always wanted to writesomething in Spanish.
I had a friend, a Cuban friend.
And we worked together and we laughedall the time, and it was just great.
And I really miss him, you know?- [Raul] Yeah.
- What I was thinking, to start off,Mi amigo Cubano, hola, como esta?
Que paso, mi hermano, and I don't knowwhether you would say tu or usted there,
but one or the other, I'll just sayTu y yo no mas hablar.
- [Raul] Yeah, tu, definitely,because you're good friends.
- Now your background is what, Raul?
- [Raul] My background ismy mother was African-American
and my father is Argentinian.
When I lived in Miami, I got verydeeply involved in Cuban music,
the music of guaguanco.- [Bill humming]
- In guaguanco, everything goes together,so there's the clave, right?
[Raul taps a rhythm]- [Bill] Okay.
- And then it goes, ♪ boom boomboom boom, boom boom boom boom ♪
♪ boom boom boom boom, you know,as you're doing all that,
you sing and you keep all that going.
♪ Ae, ae, ae la chambelona ♪ ♪ Ae, ae, ae la chambelona ♪
[Raul singing in Spanish]
- You know what I'm saying?
- Yeah, Raul.♪ [music] ♪
Yeah, man! We're going to use allthat stuff you know, Raul.
That's about all the previewI would like to do on that.
Let's just walk in with a blank sheet ofpaper
and see what we can mark on it.
- [Raul] Sounds good to me. - Yeah.
♪ [music] ♪
♪ Sometimes a song is funkyCoz you feel that way ♪
♪ A song might be easyand melancholy on another day ♪
♪ Sometimes a song gets mean and evilCoz it ain't going right ♪
♪ Sometimes a song just mightget nervous coz you might be uptight. ♪
- [Raul] I don't even knowwhat chords he has,
so it's all going to be kind ofa question of openness.
I'm going to bring what I have to the tableand hopefully come up with something.
I mean, I just felt very honored.
- Dad?
♪ Sometimes a song is tender,sometimes a song is sad. ♪
- [Bill] Hey, bud.
♪ Maybe that evening that you wrotethe song that's all the feeling you had. ♪
- [Bill] How you doing, Raul?
Let's walk in here to the studio.
♪ Sometimes a song just feels real goodand lays right there in the groove. ♪
- [Raul] Feels like a studio.- [Bill] Yeah?
I'm going to be largely dependent on youbecause I have no skills, Raul.
- [Raul] Well I am--yeah.- [Bill] See, you're the virtuoso.
No, I'm serious.
I got this stuff in here,I can't play any of this stuff.
[Raul laughing]
- [Raul] I learned, you know what,instead of putting myself in a situation
where my blindness makes me inferior,I'm going to create a situation where
I can put my strengths out there.
I think that when you're disabled inany way or when you have some--
I think you have to figure outhow you learn.
- [Bill] But you know what, Raul?You use the word disabled.
- [Raul] Right.
- [Bill] You are enabled in other areasthat the average person doesn't have.
I was a stutterer until I was 28.I used to avoid the phone and, you know,
just anywhere where you had to talk.
And people would get up in your faceand say, "Spit it out, spit it out!"
As if you had a choice in the matter,you know what I mean?
- [Raul] Yeah.
- As if you got in that line and said,"Well, I think I'm going to get in",
you know, when you're getting ready- [Raul] Ready.
- [Bill] to be born like,"I think I'll get in the stuttering line."
[Raul laughing]- [Bill] And the thing is,
what do you do after youfind out you're here?
So then, you know, there was a phrasethat I kept batting around,
"In my mind's eye, I can seethe world from here."
- [Raul] Right. Wow.
- [Bill] How's that?
- [Raul] I love it.- [Bill] You want to play with that later?
- [Raul] Yes.- [Bill] Why don't you write it down
so you don't forget it.- [Raul] I'm writing it down.
I love it, and it could be somethingabout being clear.
The mind--- [Bill] Yeah. Okay, write down "clear".
"I can see the world from here."- [Raul] Yeah.
So because it's--- [Bill] "And sometimes I--"
- [Raul] Because clarity in themind's eye, is absolute.
It can be absolute.
- [Bill] Okay. Okay, now let's beginanother line.
- [Raul] I can hear the dream-my dream, so clear.
- [Bill] Yeah.- [Raul] Just an idea, just an idea.
Okay.- [Bill] That's good, Raul. That's good.
"In my mind's eye",[together] "I can see the world from here."
[together] "And sometimes I can hearmy dreams so clear."
- Get down, Raul, come on, brother.[Raul laughing]
Throw something in the pot. There you go.[Raul laughing]
- [Raul] Because people always ask meabout dreams.
"How do you dream if you can't see?""Well, I hear in my dreams, don't you?"
- [Bill] Yeah.- [Raul ]You know what I mean?
It's not about seeing,it's about being in your dream.
♪ [guitar playing] ♪
- [Kori] I don't know what wouldmotivate someone
at the point in their life that he's in,with the break that he's taken.
But I do know that he has no problem
throwing down when he feelslike throwing down.
When he wants to do something, I mean, he's just obsessed.
He's all in, up at two o'clockin the morning, not eating, not sleeping,
and that's exhausting.
- [Bill] ♪ Mi amigo ♪- [Raul] ♪ Mi amigo Cubano. ♪
- Yeah.No, I'm looking for the count-in.
♪ Hola, como esta? ♪
- [together] ♪ Mi amigo Cubano ♪
[Bill and Raul singing]♪ Que paso, mi hermano? ♪
[guitar playing]
- Yeah. Something like that.
♪ Mi amigo Cubano ♪
[Raul singing Spanish]
- [Bill] There you go, Raul.That's what I'm talking about.
- [Raul] That was pretty cool, actually.- [Bill] You know, you know.
It all gets back to that thing.
If you start sweet then you got somewhere to go.
Let me go to 41 hereand see what's happening, Raul.
Bear with me here,one more time, okay?
Listen to this and then I'll makemy next edit, okay?
♪ [music] ♪
♪ Hola, como esta? ♪
- [Marcia] I think Bill isalways thinking of songs.
He has songs that he's created overthe last 10, 15 years that are on tape.
He put a lot into building that studio.
I think in his imagination, he felt,"I'm going to do some music."
Whether or not he was gonna actuallyput it out there,
that's another story.
- [Bill] Background- [together] ♪ Amigo cubano! ♪
- [Bill]♪ Ba-do be-da-boo-dee... ♪
- Selfishly, it would be fantastic.
Fantastic, if he would get a recordtogether and it would be new music
and all that kind of stuff.
It would be fun, but realistically,I'm not sure that he wants that.
He just hasn't wanted to get backinto the music business.
- [together] ♪ Que paso, mi hermano. ♪[Raul imitates a trumpet]
- [Bill] I'm going to go to the Carnival here.
♪ Mi amigo Cubano. ♪
- [Bill] There it is, there.
Yeah, there it is, there it is.
♪ Mi amigo Cubano ♪
- It's got that hump with it.
♪ Que paso, mi hermano? ♪
- I might just go in this frenzy,you know,
just become obsessed with it every day.
All you hear is just noise and me.You know what I mean?
I would like that.
[Bill playing piano ang singing]
Let's figure it out.♪ Waay-oh... ♪
♪ There's just so much about you ♪
♪ That I like ♪
♪ And it's been so good to knowHow you've always--♪
♪been there for me ♪
♪ When I needed a friend ♪
♪ And oh, by the way ♪
♪ Any time, any time ♪
♪ Any time of the night or day ♪
♪ I will be just... ♪
♪a telephone call away. ♪
- Come on, Kori, sing that bridge.
- [Kori singing]♪ Say if you need me ♪
♪ I'll always be ♪
♪just a telephone call away ♪
- [Bill] Go ahead, sing it.- ♪ And oh, by the way ♪
♪ I just want to say ♪♪ Any time, any time ♪
♪ Any time of the night or dayI will be just a telephone call away. ♪
- [together] Yeah.
- [Bill] Ha-ha-ha! Let's get out of here.
- [Kori] That sounded really nice.- [Bill] But Kori, girl,
we can work that tune.
- [Kori] We can.- [Bill] We can do that song.
- Yeah.
As far as music goes, I think my dadis a pretty honest critic,
and I really had to toughen upand realize that there's a difference
between someone criticizing youin a way that's saying, "you're untalented"
and someone being a coach,you know, someone saying,
"Yeah, that wasn't a strike."
- [Bill] You ain't no joke, sugar.- [Kori] No.
- That was so great to sing in that room.The acoustic--
- [Bill] Yeah. You gettinga little grease on you,
that's what I'm talking about,you understand?
You know, getting a little greaseon you, that is--
you bringing the stuff, Kori.[Kori laughing]
- Let's hit this sucker here.
Yeah.
- [Kori] I knew there are waysthat my father is gifted,
and that I'm different than that, and thatI'm going to have to find my own process
and sort of my own way, and for meI just knew that I wanted to get better.
- [Bill] You just be comfortable--- [Kori] Okay.
- [Bill] and we'll make all this work.- [Kori talking]
- [Bill] Yeah. - [Kori] I'm going to lift this just slightly.
- [Bill] Do what you want to with it.You want it closer, further away?
- [Kori] No, that's good. This is a--This is called Blue Blues.
[Kori playing piano]♪ [music] ♪
♪ I've moved on from you ♪♪ So I say-- so it seems ♪
♪ You have gone far away ♪♪ I let you go, I set you free ♪
♪ Still I swim in a sea ♪♪ Of you.. My blue... ♪
- [Kori] My biggest fear,worst nightmare, was that
I would be a disappointment to him,that I would show him what I had
and he would be disappointed.
Because I knew he alwayswas really eager
to work with me,and I was always just like,
"Why? You're Bill Withers.Why would you ever want to do that?"
Like, "why would you ever wantto do that?"
And I just could never see how heand I could sit in a room as equals
and do anything together.
[Kori singing]
♪ I give up, I give in ♪♪ I can't hide away this love I'm in ♪
♪ Will never have me ♪♪ Will only leave me ♪
♪ Deep in the sea of my blue,blue blues. ♪
- [Bill] Oh, that's great.- [Kori] Oh, I'm sorry. [laughing]
- I'm just--I'm just glad to see you.[Bill sniffing]
[Bill sobbing] You know what I mean.- [Kori] Yeah.
- [Bill] Let's hear that.
Let's hear that.
♪ [music] ♪
- We're all accidents at birth, you know?
We don't get to choose what we look like,
we don't get to choosehow gifted we're going to be,
how tall, how strong, how--
we don't get to choose anything aboutwhat we're going to be.
One day, somebody says, "You ARE."
At some point or another,we have a choice...
If we're sane enough by that point, as tohow much we're going to apply ourselves,
and a lot of that is influencedby the people who nurture us.
I already did what I did.
I'm not that little boy or that young guyany more that hasn't had any validation.
♪ [music] ♪
♪ Grandma's hand ♪♪ Clapped in church on Sunday morning ♪
♪ Grandma's hand ♪♪ Played a tambourine so well ♪
♪ Grandma's hand ♪♪ Issued out a warning ♪
♪ Billy, don't you run so fast ♪♪ Might fall on a piece of glass ♪
♪ Might be snakes there in that grass ♪♪ Grandma's hand ♪
♪ And you know that Grandma's hands ♪♪ Soothed a local unwed mother ♪
♪ Grandma's hand ♪♪ It aches some times and swells ♪
♪ Grandma's hands ♪♪ Lift her face and tell her ♪
♪ Baby, Grandma, understand ♪♪ That your really love that man ♪
♪ Even though he ain't no good ♪♪ Grandma's hand... ♪
- Come on, play it, man.
♪ [music] ♪
[waves crashing]
♪ [Who is he(And what is he to you) playing] ♪